<annotatedpaper>
    <paper title="Learning Subjective Language " authors="Janyce Wiebe, Theresa Wilson, Rebecca Bruce, Matthew Bell, Melanie Martin" year="2011"> 
        <section> 
            <title>Learning Subjective Language </title> 
            Janyce Wiebe∗ Theresa Wilson† 
            University of Pittsburgh University of Pittsburgh 
            Rebecca Bruce‡ Matthew Bell∗ 
            University of North Carolina University of Pittsburgh 
            at Asheville 
            Melanie Martin§ 
            New Mexico State University   
        </section> 
        <section> 
            <title>Abstract</title> 
            <paragraph> 
                Subjectivity in natural language refers to aspects of language used to express opinions, evaluations, and speculations. There are numerous natural language processing applications for which subjectivity analysis is relevant, including information extraction and text categorization. The goal ofthis work is learning subjective language from corpora. Clues ofsubjectivity are generated and tested, including low-frequency words, collocations, and adjectives and verbs identified using distributional similarity. The features are also examined working together in concert. The features, generated from different data sets using different procedures, exhibit consistency in performance in that they all do better and worse on the same data sets. In addition, this article shows that the density of subjectivity clues in the surrounding context strongly affects how likely it is that a word is subjective, and it provides the results ofan annotation study assessing the subjectivity ofsentences with high-density features. Finally, the clues are used to perform opinion piece recognition (a type oftext categorization and genre detection) to demonstrate the utility of the knowledge acquired in this article. 
            </paragraph> 
        </section> 
        <section imrad="i"> 
            <title>1. Introduction</title> 
            <paragraph> 
                
                <context>
                    Subjectivity in natural language refers to aspects of language used to express opinions, evaluations, and speculations <cite id="1" function="ack" polarity="neu">(Banfield 1982; Wiebe 1994)</cite>. 
                </context>
                
                Many natural language processing (NLP) applications could benefit from being able to distinguish subjective language from language used to objectively present factual information. Current extraction and retrieval technology focuses almost exclusively on the subject matter of documents. 
                <context>
                    However, additional aspects of a document influence its relevance, including evidential status and attitude <cite id="2" function="ack" polarity="neu">(Kessler, Nunberg, Schutze 1997)</cite>. 
                </context>
                Information extraction systems should be able to distinguish between factual information (which should be extracted) and nonfactual information (which should be * Department of Computer Science, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA 15260. E-mail {wiebe,mbell}@cs.pitt.edu. f Intelligent Systems Program, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA 15260. Email: twilson@cs.pitt.edu. X Department of Computer Science, University of North Carolina at Asheville, Asheville, NC 28804. E-mail: bruce@cs.unca.edu § Department of Computer Science, New Mexico State University, Las Cruces, NM 88003. E-mail: mmartin@cs.nmsu.edu. Submission received: 20 March 2002; Revised submission received: 30 September 2003; Accepted for publication: 23 January 2004 Theresa Wilson" University of Pittsburgh Matthew Bell* University of Pittsburgh Rebecca Bruce* University of North Carolina at Asheville discarded or labeled as uncertain). 
                <context>
                    Question-answering systems should distinguish between factual and speculative answers. Multi-perspective question answering aims to present multiple answers to the user based upon speculation or opinions derived from different sources <cite id="3" function="ack" polarity="neu">(Carbonell 1979; Wiebe et al. 2003)</cite>.
                </context>
                Multidocument summarization systems should summarize different opinions and perspectives. 
                <context>
                    <method>Automatic subjectivity analysis</method> 
                    <kw>would also be useful</kw> 
                    <kw>to perform</kw> 
                    <task>flame recognition</task> 
                    <cite id="4" function="use" polarity="neu">(Spertus 1997; Kaufer 2000) </cite>, <task>e-mail classification</task> 
                    <cite id="5" function="use" polarity="neu">(Aone, Ramos-Santacruze, and Niehaus 2000)</cite>, <task>intellectual attribution in text</task> 
                    <cite id="6" function="use" polarity="neu">(Teufel and Moens 2000) </cite>, <task>recognition of speaker role in radio broadcasts</task> 
                    <cite id="7" function="use" polarity="neu">(Barzialy et al. 2000) </cite>, <task>review mining</task> 
                    <cite id="8" function="use" polarity="neu">(Terveen et al. 1997)</cite>, <task>review classification</task> 
                    <cite id="9" function="use" polarity="neu">(Turney 2002; Pang, Lee, and Vaithyanathan 2002)</cite>, <task>style in generation</task> 
                    <cite id="10" function="use" polarity="neu">(Hovy 1987)</cite>, and <task>clustering documents by ideological point of view</task> 
                    <cite id="11" function="use" polarity="neu">(Sack 1995)</cite>. 
                </context>
                In general, nearly any information-seeking system could benefit from knowledge of how opinionated a text is and whether or not the writer purports to objectively present factual material. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                
                To perform automatic subjectivity analysis, good clues must be found.
                <context>
                    A huge variety of words and phrases have subjective usages, and <kw>while some manually developed resources exist</kw>, <kw>such as</kw> 
                    <data>dictionaries of affective language</data> 
                    <cite id="12" function="wea" polarity="neg" >(General-Inquirer 2000; Heise 2000)</cite> and subjective features in general-purpose lexicons (e.g., the attitude adverb features in Comlex <cite id="13" function="wea" polarity="neg">[Macleod, Grishman, and Meyers 1998])</cite>,  <kw>there is no comprehensive</kw> 
                    <data>dictionary of subjective language</data>.
                </context>
               


                In addition, many expressions with subjective usages have objective usages as well, so a dictionary alone would not suffice. An NLP system must disambiguate these expressions in context. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The goal of our work is learning subjective language from corpora. In this article, we generate and test subjectivity clues and contextual features and use the knowledge we gain to recognize subjective sentences and opinionated documents. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Two kinds of data are available to us: a relatively small amount of data manually annotated at the expression level (i.e., labels on individual words and phrases) of Wall Street Journal and newsgroup data and a large amount of data with existing document-level annotations from the Wall Street Journal (opinion pieces, such as editorials and reviews, versus nonopinion pieces). Both are used as training data to identify clues of subjectivity. In addition, we cross-validate the results between the two types of annotation: The clues learned from the expression-level data are evaluated against the document-level annotations, and those learned using the document-level annotations are evaluated against the expression-level annotations. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                There were a number of motivations behind our decision to use document-level annotations, in addition to our manual annotations, to identify and evaluate clues of subjectivity. The document-level annotations were not produced according to our annotation scheme and were not produced for the purpose of training and evaluating an NLP system. Thus, they are an external influence from outside the laboratory. In addition, there are a great number of these data, enabling us to evaluate the results on a larger scale, using multiple large test sets. This and cross-training between the two types of annotations allows us to assess consistency in performance of the various identification procedures. Good performance in cross-validation experiments between different types of annotations is evidence that the results are not brittle. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                We focus on three types of subjectivity clues. The first are hapax legomena, the set of words that appear just once in the corpus. We refer to them here as unique words. The set of all unique words is a feature with high frequency and significantly higher precision than baseline (Section 3.2). 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The second are collocations (Section 3.3). We demonstrate a straightforward method for automatically identifying collocational clues of subjectivity in texts. The method is first used to identify fixed n-grams, such as of the century and get out of here. Interestingly, many include noncontent words that are typically on stop lists of NLP systems (e.g., of, the, get, out, here in the above examples). The method is then used to identify an unusual form of collocation: One or more positions in the collocation may be filled by any word (of an appropriate part of speech) that is unique in the test data. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                
                <context>
                    The third type of subjectivity clue <author>we</author> 
                    <kw>examine here</kw> 
                    <concept>are adjective and verb features</concept> 
                    <kw>identified using</kw> 
                    <result>the results of a method</result> for clustering words according to distributional similarity <cite id="14" function="bas" polarity="neu">(Lin 1998)</cite> (Section 3.4).
                </context>
                We hypothesized that two words may be distributionally similar because they are both potentially subjective (e.g., tragic, sad, and poignant are identified from bizarre). In addition, we use distributional similarity to improve estimates of unseen events: A word is selected or discarded based on the precision of it together with its n most similar neighbors. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                We show that the various subjectivity clues perform better and worse on the same data sets, exhibiting an important consistency in performance (Section 4.2). 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                In addition to learning and evaluating clues associated with subjectivity, we address disambiguating them in context, that is, identifying instances of clues that are subjective in context (Sections 4.3 and 4.4). We find that the density of clues in the surrounding context is an important influence. Using two types of annotations serves us well here, too. It enables us to use manual judgments to identify parameters for disambiguating instances of automatically identified clues. High-density clues are high precision in both the expression-level and document-level data. In addition, we give the results of a new annotation study showing that most high-density clues are in subjective text spans (Section 4.5). Finally, we use the clues together to perform document-level classification, to further demonstrate the utility of the acquired knowledge (Section 4.6). 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                At the end of the article, we discuss related work (Section 5) and conclusions (Section 6). 
            </paragraph> 
        </section> 
        <section imrad="m"> 
            <title>2. Subjectivity</title> 
            <paragraph> 
                Subjective language is language used to express private states in the context of a text or conversation. Private state is a general covering term for opinions, evaluations, emotions, and speculations (Quirk et al. 1985). The following are examples of subjective sentences from a variety of document types. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The first two examples are from Usenet newsgroup messages: 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                (1) I had in mind your facts, buddy, not hers. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                (2) Nice touch. "Alleges" whenever facts posted are not in your persona of what is "real." The next one is from an editorial: 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                (3) We stand in awe of the Woodstock generation's ability to be unceasingly fascinated by the subject of itself. ("Bad Acid," Wall Street Journal, The next example is from a book review: 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                (4) At several different layers, it's a fascinating tale. (George Melloan, "Whose Spying on Our Computers?" Wall Street Journal, November 1, The last one is from a news story: 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                (5) "The cost of health care is eroding our standard of living and sapping industrial strength," complains Walter Maher, a Chrysler health-and-benefits specialist. (Kenneth H. Bacon, "Business and Labor Reach a Consensus on Need to Overhaul Health-Care System," Wall Street Journal, November 1, 1989) In contrast, the following are examples of objective sentences, sentences without significant expressions of subjectivity: 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                (6) Bell Industries Inc. increased its quarterly to 10 cents from 7 cents a share. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                (7) Northwest Airlines settled the remaining lawsuits filed on behalf of 156 people killed in a 1987 crash, but claims against the jetliner's maker are being pursued, a federal judge said. ("Northwest Airlines Settles Rest of Suits," Wall Street Journal, November 1, 1989) 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                A particular model of linguistic subjectivity underlies the current and past research in this area by Wiebe and colleagues. It is most fully presented in Wiebe and research and combines ideas from several sources in fields outside NLP, especially linguistics and literary theory.
                <context>
                    <kw>The most direct</kw> 
                    <kw>influences on</kw> 
                    <method>the model</method> 
                    <kw>were</kw> 
                    <cite id="15" function="bas" polarity="pos">Dolezel (1973)</cite> (types of subjectivity clues), <cite id="16" function="bas" polarity="pos">Uspensky (1973)</cite> (types of point of view), <cite id="17" function="bas" polarity="pos">Kuroda (1973, 1976)</cite> (pragmatics of point of view), <cite id="18" function="bas" polarity="pos">Chatman (1978)</cite> (story versus discourse), <cite id="19" function="bas" polarity="pos">Cohn (1978)</cite> (linguistic styles for presenting consciousness), <cite id="20" function="bas" polarity="pos">Fodor (1979)</cite> (linguistic description of opaque contexts), and especially <cite id="21" function="bas" polarity="pos">Banfield (1982)</cite> (theory of subjectivity versus communication).  
                </context>
                
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The remainder of this section sketches our conceptualization of subjectivity and describes the annotation projects it underlies. Subjective elements are linguistic expressions of private states in context. Subjective elements are often lexical (examples are stand in awe, unceasingly, fascinated in (3) and eroding, sapping, and complains in (5)). They may be single words (e.g., complains) or more complex expressions (e.g., stand in awe, what a NP). Purely syntactic or morphological devices may also be subjective elements (e.g., fronting, parallelism, changes in aspect). 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                A subjective element expresses the subjectivity of a source, who may be the writer or someone mentioned in the text. For example, the source of fascinating in (4) is the writer, while the source of the subjective elements in (5) is Maher (according to the writer). In addition, a subjective element usually has a target, that is, what the subjectivity is about or directed toward. In (4), the target is a tale; in (5), the target of Maher's subjectivity is the cost of health care. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Note our parenthetical above—"according to the writer"—concerning Maher's subjectivity. Maher is not directly speaking to us but is being quoted by the writer. Thus, the source is a nested source, which we notate (writer, Maher); this represents the fact that the subjectivity is being attributed to Maher by the writer. Since sources 1
                <context>
                    For additional citations to relevant work from outside NLP, please see <cite id="22" function="ack" polarity="neu">Banfield (1982)</cite>, <cite id="23" function="ack" polarity="neu">Fludernik (1993)</cite>, <cite id="24" function="ack" polarity="neu">Wiebe (1994)</cite>, and Stein and <cite id="25" function="ack" polarity="neu">Wright (1995)</cite>. 
                </context>
                are not directly addressed by the experiments presented in this article, we merely illustrate the idea here with an example, to give the reader an idea: 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The Foreign Ministry said Thursday that it was "surprised, to put it mildly" by the U.S. State Department s criticism of Russia s human rights record and objected in particular to the "odious" section on Chechnya. (Moscow Times, March 8, 2002] 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Let us consider some of the subjective elements in this sentence, along with their sources: surprised, to put it mildly: (writer, Foreign Ministry, Foreign Ministry) to put it mildly: (writer, Foreign Ministry) criticism: (writer, Foreign Ministry, Foreign Ministry, U.S. State Department) objected: (writer, Foreign Ministry) odious: (writer, Foreign Ministry) 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Consider surprised, to put it mildly. This refers to a private state of the Foreign Ministry (i.e., it is very surprised). This is in the context of The Foreign Ministrysaid, which is in a sentence written by the writer. This gives us the three-level source (writer, Foreign Ministry, Foreign Ministry). The phrase to put it mildly, which expresses sarcasm, is attributed to the Foreign Ministry by the writer (i.e., according to the writer, the Foreign Ministry said this). So its source is (writer, Foreign Ministry). The subjective element criticism has a deeply nested source: According to the writer, the Foreign Ministry said it is surprised by the U.S. State Department s criticism. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The nested-source representation allows us to pinpoint the subjectivity in a sentence. For example, there is no subjectivity attributed directly to the writer in the above sentence: At the level of the writer, the sentence merely says that someone said something and objected to something (without evaluating or questioning this). If the sentence started The magnificent Foreign Ministry said..., then we would have an additional subjective element, magnificent, with source (writer). 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Note that subjective does not mean not true. Consider the sentence John criticized Mary for smoking. The verb criticized is a subjective element, expressing negative evaluation, with nested source (writer, John). But this does not mean that John does not believe that Mary smokes. (In addition, the fact that John criticized Mary is being presented as true by the writer.) 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Similarly, objective does not mean true. A sentence is objective if the language used to convey the information suggests that facts are being presented; in the context of the discourse, material is objectively presented as if it were true. Whether or not the source truly believes the information, and whether or not the information is in fact true, are considerations outside the purview of a theory of linguistic subjectivity. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                An aspect of subjectivity highlighted when we are working with NLP applications is ambiguity. Many words with subjective usages may be used objectively. Examples are sapping and eroding. In (5), they are used subjectively, but one can easily imagine objective usages, in a scientific domain, for example. Thus, an NLP system may not merely consult a list of lexical items to accurately identify subjective language but must disambiguate words, phrases, and sentences in context. In our terminology, a potential subjective element (PSE) is a linguistic element that may be used to express subjectivity. 
                <context>
                    A subjective element is an instance of a potential subjective element, in a particular context, that is indeed subjective in that context <cite id="26" function="ack" polarity="neu">(Wiebe 1994)</cite>.
                </context>
                In this article, we focus on learning lexical items that are associated with subjectivity (i.e., PSEs) and then using them in concert to disambiguate instances of them (i.e., to determine whether the instances are subjective elements). 
            </paragraph> 
       
        
            <title>2.1 Manual Annotations</title> 
            <paragraph> 
                In our subjectivity annotation projects, we do not give the annotators lists of particular words and phrases to look for. Rather, we ask them to label sentences according to their interpretations in context. As a result, the annotators consider a large variety of expressions when performing annotations. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                We use data that have been manually annotated at the expression level, the sentence level, and the document level. For diversity, we use data from the Wall Street Journal Treebank as well as data from a corpus of Usenet newsgroup messages. Table 1 summarizes the data sets and annotations used in this article. None of the datasets overlap. The annotation types listed in the table are those used in the experiments presented in this article. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                <context>
                    <author>In our</author> 
                    <experiment>first subjectivity annotation project</experiment> 
                    <cite id="27" function="bas" polarity="pos">(Wiebe, Bruce, and O'Hara 1999; Bruce and Wiebe 1999)</cite>, <data>a corpus of sentences</data> 
                    <kw>from</kw> 
                    <data>the Wall Street Journal Treebank Corpus</data> (<cite id="28" function="bas" polarity="pos">Marcus, Santorini, and Marcinkiewicz 1993)</cite> (corpus WSJ-SE in Table 1) <action>was annotated</action> at the sentence level by multiple judges.
                </context>
                The judges were instructed to classify a sentence as subjective if it contained any significant expressions of subjectivity, attributed to either the writer or someone mentioned in the text, and to classify the sentence as objective, otherwise. After multiple rounds of training, the annotators independently annotated a fresh test set of 500 sentences from WSJ-SE. They achieved an average pairwise kappa score of 0.70 over the entire test set, an average pairwise kappa score of 0.80 for the 85% of the test set for which the annotators were somewhat sure of their judgments, and an average pairwise kappa score of 0.88 for the 70% of the test set for which the annotators were very sure of their judgments. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                We later asked the same annotators to identify the subjective elements in WSJ-SE. Specifically, each annotator was given the subjective sentences he identified in the previous study and asked to put brackets around the words he believed caused the sentence to be classified as subjective. For example (subjective elements are in parentheses): 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                They paid (yet) more for (really good stuff). (Perhaps you'll forgive me) for reposting his response. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                No other instructions were given to the annotators and no training was performed for the expression-level task. A single round of tagging was performed, with no communication between annotators. 
                <context>
                    <kw>There are</kw> 
                    <method>techniques</method> 
                    <kw>for</kw> 
                    <task>analyzing agreement</task> when annotations involve segment boundaries <cite id="29" function="use" polarity="neu">(Litman and Passonneau 1995; Marcu, Romera, and Amorortu 1999)</cite>, <kw>but our focus</kw> in this article <kw>is on words</kw>. 
                </context>
                
                Thus, our analyses are at the word level: Each word is classified as either appearing in a subjective element or not. Punctuation and numbers are excluded from the analyses. The kappa value for word agreement in this study is 0.42. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                <context>
                    Another two-level annotation project was performed in <cite id="30" function="ack" polarity="neu">Wiebe et al. (2001)</cite>, this time involving document-level and expression-level annotations of newsgroup data (NG-FE in Table 1).
                </context>
                In that project, we were interested in annotating flames, inflammatory messages in newsgroups or listservs. Note that inflammatory language is a kind of subjective language. The annotators were instructed to mark a message as a flame if the main intention of the message is a personal attack and the message contains insulting or abusive language. After multiple rounds of training, three annotators independently annotated a fresh test set of 88 messages from NG-FE. The average pairwise percentage agreement is 92% and the average pairwise kappa value is 0.78. 
                <context>
                    These results are comparable to those of <cite id="31" function="ack" polarity="neu">Spertus (1997)</cite>, who reports 98% agreement on noninflammatory messages and 64% agreement on inflammatory messages. 
                </context>
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Two of the annotators were then asked to identify the flame elements in the entire corpus NG-FE. Flame elements are the subset of subjective elements that are perceived to be inflammatory. The two annotators were asked to do this in the entire corpus, even those messages not identified as flames, because messages that were not judged to be flames at the document level may contain some individual inflammatory phrases. As above, no training was performed for the expression-level task, and a single round of tagging was performed, without communication between annotators. Agreement was measured in the same way as in the subjective-element study above. The kappa value for flame element annotations in corpus NG-FE is 0.46. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                An additional annotation project involved a single annotator, who performed subjective-element annotations on the newsgroup corpus NG-SE. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The agreement results above suggest that good levels of agreement can be achieved at higher levels of classification (sentence and document), but agreement at the expression level is more challenging. The agreement values are lower for the expression-level annotations but are still much higher than that expected by chance. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Note that our word-based analysis of agreement is a tough measure, because it requires that exactly the same words be identified by both annotators. Consider the following example from WSJ-SE: 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                D: (played the role well) (obligatory ragged jeans a thicket of long hair and rejection of all things conventional) 2 We are grateful to Aravind Joshi for suggesting this level of annotation. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                M: played the role (well) (obligatory) (ragged) jeans a (thicket) of long hair and (rejection) of (all things conventional) 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Judge D in the example consistently identifies entire phrases as subjective, while judge M prefers to select discrete lexical items. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Despite such differences between annotators, the expression-level annotations proved very useful for exploring hypotheses and generating features, as described below. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                <context>
                    <kw>Since this</kw> 
                    <paper>article</paper> 
                    <kw>was written</kw>, <tool>a new annotation project</tool> 
                    <kw>has been completed</kw>. A 10,000-sentence corpus of English-language versions of world news articles has been annotated with detailed subjectivity information as part of a project investigating multiple-perspective question answering <cite id="32" function="ack" polarity="pos">(Wiebe et al. 2003)</cite>. <posfeature>These annotations are much more detailed</posfeature> 
                    <kw>than</kw> 
                    <data>the annotations used in this article</data> (including, for example, the source of each private state).
                </context>
                <context>
                    <concept>The interannotator agreement scores</concept> 
                    <kw>for the new</kw> 
                    <data>corpus</data> 
                    <posfeature>are high and are improvements</posfeature> over the results of the studies described above <cite id="33" function="ack" polarity="pos">(Wilson and Wiebe 2003)</cite>. 
                </context>
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The current article uses existing document-level subjective classes, namely editorials, letters to the editor, Arts &amp; Leisure reviews, and Viewpoints in the Wall Street Journal. These are subjective classes in the sense that they are text categories for which subjectivity is a key aspect. We refer to them collectively as opinion pieces. All other types of documents in the Wall Street Journal are collectively referred to as nonopinion pieces. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Note that opinion pieces are not 100% subjective. For example, editorials contain objective sentences presenting facts supporting the writer s argument, and reviews contain sentences objectively presenting facts about the product beign reviewed. Similarly, nonopinion pieces are not 100% objective.
                <context>
                    News reports present opinions and reactions to reported events<cite id="34" fucntion="ack" polarity="neu"> (van Dijk 1988)</cite>; they often contain segments starting with expressions such as critics claim and supporters argue.
                </context>
                
                <context>
                    In addition, quoted-speech sentences in which individuals express their subjectivity are often included <cite id="35" function="ack" polarity="neu">(Barzilay et al. 2000)</cite>.  
                </context>
                


                For concreteness, let us consider WSJ-SE, which, recall, has been manually annotated at the sentence level. In WSJ-SE, 70% of the sentences in opinion pieces are subjective and 30% are objective. In nonopinion pieces, 44% of the sentences are subjective and only 56% are objective. Thus, while there is a higher concentration of subjective sentences in opinion versus nonopinion pieces, there are many subjective sentences in nonopinion pieces and objective sentences in opinion pieces. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                An inspection of some data reveals that some editorial and review articles are not marked as such by the Wall Street Journal. For example, there are articles whose purpose is to present an argument rather than cover a news story, but they are not explicitly labeled as editorials by the Wall Street Journal. Thus, the opinion piece annotations of data sets OP1 and OP2 in Table 1 have been manually refined. The annotation instructions were simply to identify any additional opinion pieces that were not marked as such. To test the reliability of this annotation, two judges independently annotated two Wall Street Journal files, W9-22 and W9-33, each containing approximately 160,000 words. This is an "annotation lite" task: With no training, the annotators achieved kappa values of 0.94 and 0.95, and each spent an average of three hours per Wall Street Journal file. 
            </paragraph> 
   
         
            <title>3. Generating and Testing Subjective Features</title> 
            <subsection> 
                <title> 3.1 Introduction</title> 
                <paragraph> 
                    The goal in this section is to learn lexical subjectivity clues of various types, single words as well as collocations. Some require no training data, some are learned using the expression-level subjective-element annotations as training data, and some are learned using the document-level opinion piece annotations as training data (i.e., opinion piece versus nonopinion piece). All of the clues are evaluated with respect to the document-level opinion piece annotations. While these evaluations are our focus, because many more opinion piece than subjective-element data exist, we do evaluate the clues learned from the opinion piece data on the subjective-element data as well. Thus, we cross-validate the results both ways between the two types of annotations. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Throughout this section, we evaluate sets of clues directly, by measuring the proportion of clues that appear in subjective documents or expressions, seeking those that appear more often than expected. In later sections, the clues are used together to find subjective sentences and to perform text categorization. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    The following paragraphs give details of the evaluation and experimental design used in this section. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    The proportion of clues in subjective documents or expressions is their precision. Specifically, the precision of a set S with respect to opinion pieces is number of instances of members of S in opinion pieces total number of instances of members of S in the data The precision of a set S with respect to subjective elements is number of instances of members of S in subjective elements In the above, S is a set of types (not tokens). The counts are of tokens (i.e., instances or occurrences) of members of S. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Why use a set rather than individual items? Many good clues of subjectivity occur with low frequency (Wiebe, McKeever, and Bruce 1998). In fact, as we shall see below, uniqueness in the corpus is an informative feature for subjectivity classification. Thus, we do not want to discard low-frequency clues, because they are a valuable source of information, and we do not want to evaluate individual low-frequency lexical items, because the results would be unreliable. Our strategy is thus to identify and evaluate sets of words and phrases, rather than individual items. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    What kinds of results may we expect? We cannot expect absolutely high precision with respect to the opinion piece classifications, even for strong clues, for three reasons. First, for our purposes, the data are noisy. As mentioned above, while the proportion of subjective sentences is higher in opinion than in nonopinion pieces, the proportions are not 100 and 0: Opinion pieces contain objective sentences, and nonopinion pieces contain subjective sentences. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Second, we are trying to learn lexical items associated with subjectivity, that is, PSEs. As discussed above, many words and phrases with subjective usages have objective usages as well. Thus, even in perfect data with no noise, we would not expect 100% precision. (This is the motivation for the work on density presented in section 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Third, the distribution of opinions and nonopinions is highly skewed in favor of nonopinions: Only 9% of the articles in the combination of OP1 and OP2 are opinion pieces. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    In this work, increases in precision over a baseline precision are used as evidence that promising sets of PSEs have been found. Our main baseline for comparison is the number of word instances in opinion pieces, divided by the total number of word instances: number of word instances in opinion pieces total number of word instances Frequencies and increases in precision of unique words in subjective-element data. Baseline frequency is the total number of words, and baseline precision is the proportion of words in subjective elements. Words and phrases with higher proportions than this appear more than expected in opinion pieces. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    To further evaluate the quality of a set of PSEs, we also perform the following significance test. For a set of PSEs in a given data set, we test the significance of the difference between (1) the proportion of words in opinion pieces that are PSEs and (2) the proportion of words in nonopinion pieces that are PSEs, using the z-significance test for two proportions. Before we continue, there are a few more technical items to mention concerning the data preparation and experimental design: 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    • All of the data sets are stemmed using Karp's morphological analyzer (Karp et al. 1994) and part-of-speech tagged using Brill's (1992) tagger. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    • When the opinion piece classifications are used for training, the existing classifications, assigned by the Wall Street Journal, are used. Thus, the processes using them as training data may be applied to more data to learn more clues, without requiring additional manual annotation. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    • When the opinion piece data are used for testing, the manually refined classifications (described at the end of Section 2.1) are used. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    • OP1 and OP2 together comprise eight treebank files. Below, we often give results separately for the component files, allowing us to assess the consistency of results for the various types of clues. 
                </paragraph> 
                <title>3.2 Unique Words</title> 
                <paragraph> 
                    In this section, we show that low-frequency words are associated with subjectivity in both the subjective-element and opinion piece data. Apparently, people are creative when they are being opinionated. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph>  
                    Table 2 gives results for unique words in subjective-element data. Recall that unique words are those that appear just once in the corpus, that is, hapax legomena. The first row of Table 2 gives the frequency of unique words in WSJ-SE, followed by the percentage-point improvements in precision over baseline for unique words in subjective elements marked by two annotators (denoted as D and M in the table). The second row gives baseline frequency and precisions. Baseline frequency is the total number of words in WSJ-SE. Baseline precision for an annotator is the proportion of words included in subjective elements by that annotator. Specifically, consider anno-tator M. The baseline precision of words in subjective elements marked by M is 0.08, Frequencies and increases in precision for words that appear exactly once in the data sets composing OP1. For each data set, baseline frequency is the total number of words, and baseline precision is the proportion of words in opinion pieces. but the precision of unique words in these same annotations is 0.20, 0.12 points higher than the baseline. This is a 150% improvement over the baseline. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    The number of unique words in opinion pieces is also higher than expected. Table 3 compares the precision of the set of unique words to the baseline precision (i.e., the precision of the set of all words that appear in the corpus) in the four WSJ files composing OP1. Before this analysis was performed, numbers were removed from the data (we are not interested in the fact that, say, the number 163,213.01 appears just once in the corpus). The number of words in each data set and baseline precisions are listed at the bottom of the table. The freq columns give total frequencies. The +prec columns show the percentage-point improvements in precision over baseline. For example, in W9-10, unique words have precision 0.34: 0.18 baseline plus an improvement over baseline of 0.16. The difference in the proportion of words that are unique in opinion pieces and the proportion of words that are unique in nonopinion pieces is highly significant, with p &lt; 0.001 (z &gt; 22) for all of the data sets. Note that not only does the set of unique words have higher than baseline precision, the set is a frequent feature. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    The question arises, how does corpus size affect the precision of the set of unique words? Presumably, uniqueness in a larger corpus is more meaningful than uniqueness in a smaller one. The results in Figure 1 provide evidence that it is. The y-axis in Figure 1 represents increase in precision over baseline and the x-axis represents corpus size. Five graphs are plotted, one for the set of words that appear exactly once (uniques), one for the set of words that appear exactly twice (freq2), one for the set of words that appear exactly three times (freq3), etc. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    In Figure 1, increases in precision are given for corpora of size n, where n = 20, 40, ... , 2420, 2440 documents. Each data point is an average over 25 sample corpora of size n. The sample corpora were chosen from the concatenation of OP1 and OP2, in which 9% of the documents are opinion pieces. The sample corpora were created by randomly selecting documents from the large corpus, preserving the 9% distribution of opinion pieces. At the smallest corpus size (containing 20 documents), the average number of words is 9,617. At the largest corpus size (containing 2440 documents), the average is 1,225,186 words. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    As can be seen in the figure, the precision of unique and other low-frequency words increases with corpus size, with increases tapering off at the largest corpus size tested. Words with frequency 2 also realize a nice increase, although one that is not as dramatic, in precision over baseline. Even words of frequency 3, 4, and 5 show modest increases. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    To help us understand the importance of low-frequency words in large as opposed to small data sets, we can consider the following analogy. With collectible trading cards, rare cards are the most valuable. However, if we have some cards and are trying to determine thier value, looking in only a few packs of cards will not tell us if Figure 1 Precision of low-frequency words as corpus size increases. any of our cards are valuable. Only by looking at many packs of cards can we make a determination as to which are the rare ones. Only in samples of sufficient size is uniqueness informative. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    The results in this section suggest that an NLP system using uniqueness features to recognize subjectivity should determine uniqueness with respect to the test data augmented with an additional store of (unannotated) data. 
                </paragraph> 
                <title>3.3 Identifying Potentially Subjective Collocations from Subjective-Element and Flame-Element Annotations</title> 
                <paragraph> 
                    In this section, we describe experiments in identifying potentially subjective collocations. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph>  
                    Collocations are selected from the subjective-element data (i.e., NG-SE, NG-FE, and WSJ-SE), using the union of the annotators' tags for the data sets tagged by multiple taggers. The results are then evaluated on opinion piece data. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    The selection procedure is as follows. First, all 1-grams, 2-grams, 3-grams, and 4-grams are extracted from the data. In this work, each constituent of an n-gram is a word-stem, part-of-speech pair. For example, (in-prep the-det can-noun) is a 3-gram that matches trigrams consisting of preposition in, followed by determiner the, and ending with noun can. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    A subset of the n-grams are then selected based on precision. The precision of an n-gram is the number of subjective instances of that n-gram in the data divided by the total number of instances of that n-gram in the data. An instance of an n-gram is subjective if each word occurs in a subjective element in the data. n-grams are selected based on two criteria. First, the precision of the n-gram must be greater than the baseline precision (i.e., the proportion of all word instances that are in subjective elements). Second, the precision of the n-gram must be greater than the maximum precision of its constituents. This criterion is used to avoid selecting unnecessarily long collocations. For example, scumbag is a strongly subjective clue. If be a scumbag does not have higher precision than scumbag alone, we do not want to select it. Specifically, let (W1, W2) be a bigram consisting of consecutive words W1 and W2. (W1,W2) is identified as a potential subjective element if prec(W1, W2) > 0.1 and: 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    For trigrams, we extend the second condition as follows. Let (W1, W2, W3) be a trigram consisting of consecutive words W1, W2, and W3. The condition is then The selection of 4-grams is similar to the selection of 3-grams, comparing the 4-gram first with the maximum of the precisions of word W1 and trigram (W2, W3, W4) and then with the maximum of the precisions of trigram (W1,W2,W3) and word W4. We call the n-gram collocations identified as above fixed-n-grams. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    We also define a type of collocation called a unique generalized n-gram (ugen-n-gram). Such collocations have placeholders for unique words. As will be seen below, these are our highest-precision features. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    To find and select such generalized collocations, we first find every word that appears just once in the corpus and replace it with a new word, UNIQUE (but remembering the part of speech of the original word). In essence, we treat the set of single-instance words as a single, frequently occurring word (which occurs with various parts of speech). Precisely the same method used for extracting and selecting n-grams above is used to obtain the potentially subjective collocations with one or more positions filled by a UNIQUE, part-of-speech pair. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    To test the ugen-n-grams extracted from the subjective-element training data using the method outlined above, we assess their precision with respect to opinion piece data. As with the training data, all unique words in the test data are replaced by UNIQUE. When a ugen-n-gram is matched against the test data, the UNIQUE fillers match words (of the appropriate parts of speech) that are unique in the test data. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Table 4 shows the results of testing the fixed-n-gram and the ugen-n-gram patterns identified as described above on the four data sets composing OP1. The freq columns give total frequencies, and the +prec columns show the improvements in precision from the baseline. The number of words in each data set and baseline precisions are given at the bottom of the table. For all n-gram features besides the fixed-4-grams and ugen-4-grams, the proportion of features in opinion pieces is significantly greater than the proportion of features in nonopinion pieces. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    The question arises, how much overlap is there between instances of fixed-n-grams and instances of ugen-n-grams? In the test data of Table 4, there are a total of 8,577 fixed-n-grams instances. Only 59 of these, fewer than 1% are contained (wholly or in part) in ugen-n-gram instances. This small intersection set shows that two different types of potentially subjective collocations are being recognized. 3 Specifically, the difference between (1) the number of feature instances in opinion pieces divided by the number of words in opinion pieces and (2) the number of feature instances in nonopinion pieces divided by the number of words in nonopinion pieces is significant (p &lt; 0.05) for all data sets. Frequencies and increases in precision of fixed-n-gram and ugen-n-gram collocations learned from the subjective-element data. For each data set, baseline frequency is the total number of words, and baseline precision is the proportion of words in opinion pieces. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Randomly selected examples of our learned collocations that appear in the test data are given in Tables 5 and 6. It is interesting to note that the unique generalized collocations were learned from the training data by their matching different unique words from the ones they match in the test data. 
                </paragraph> 
                <title>3.4 Generating Features from Document-Level Annotations Using Distributional Similarity</title> 
                <paragraph> 
                    In this section, we identify adjective and verb PSEs using distributional similarity. Opinion-piece data are used for training, and (a different set of) opinion-piece data and the subjective-element data are used for testing. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    <context>
                        With distributional similarity, words are judged to be more or less similar based on their distributional patterning in text <cite id="36" function="ack" polarity="neu">(Lee 1999; Lee and Pereira 1999)</cite>. 
                    </context>
                    Our trainingPrec(s) is the precision of s in the training data validationPrec(s) is the precision of s in the validation data testPrec( s) is the precision of s in the test data (similarly for trainingFreq, validationFreq, and testFreq) S = the set of all adjectives (verbs) in the training data for T in [0. 01,0.04,...,0.70]: for n in [2,3,...,40]: retained = {} For si in S: if trainingPrec({si}U Qin) > T: retained = retained u{s}u CinRT n = retained ADJpses = ADJpses U RT,n (VERBpses = VERBpses U RT,n) Results in Table 7 show testPrec(ADJpses) and testFreq(ADJpses). Figure 2 Algorithm for selecting adjective and verb features using distributional similarity. motivation for experimenting with it to identify PSEs was twofold. First we hypothesized that words might be distributionally similar because they share pragmatic usages such as expressing subjectivity even if they are not close synonyms. Second as shown above low-frequency words appear more often in subjective texts than expected. We did not want to discard all low-frequency words from consideration but cannot effectively judge the suitability of individual words. Thus to decide whether to retain a word as a PSE we consider the precision not of the individual word but of the word together with a cluster of words similar to it. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    
                    <context>
                        Many variants of distributional similarity have been used in NLP <cite id="37" function="ack" polarity="neu" >(Lee 1999; Lee and Pereira 1999)</cite>. 
                    </context>
                    <context>
                        <cite id="38" function="bas" polarity="pos">Dekang Lin's (1998)</cite> 
                        <method>method</method> 
                        <kw>is used here.</kw>
                    </context>
                    In contrast to many implementations, which focus exclusively on verb-noun relationships, Lin's method incorporates a variety of syntactic relations. This is important for subjectivity recognition because PSEs are not limited to verb-noun relationships. In addition Lin's results are freely available. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    A set of seed words begins the process. For each seed si the precision of the set {si}uCin in the training data is calculated, where C{n is the set of n words most similar to si, according to Lin's (1998) method. If the precision of {si}UCi,n is greater than a threshold T, then the words in this set are retained as PSEs. If it is not, neither si nor the words in Ci,n are retained. The union of the retained sets will be denoted RT,n, that is, the union of all sets {si}UCi,n with precision on the training set > T. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    
                    <context>
                        In <cite id="39" function="ack" polarity="neu">Wiebe (2000)</cite>, the seeds (the sis) were extracted from the subjective-element annotations in corpus WSJ-SE. 
                    </context>
                    Specifically, the seeds were the adjectives that appear at least once in a subjective element in WSJ-SE. In this article, the opinion piece corpus is used to move beyond the manual annotations and small corpus of the earlier work, and a much looser criterion is used to choose the initial seeds: All of the adjectives (verbs) in the training data are used. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    The algorithm for the process is given in Figure 2. There is one small difference for adjectives and verbs noted in the figure, that is, the precision threshold of 0.28 for Frequencies and increases in precision for adjective and verb features identified using distributional similarity with filtering. For each test data set, baseline frequency is the total number of words, and baseline precision is the proportion of words in opinion pieces. adjectives versus 0.23 for verbs. These thresholds were determined using validation data. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Seeds and their clusters are assessed on a training set for many parameter settings (cluster size n from 2 through 40, and precision threshold T from 0.01 through 0.70 by . 03). As mentioned above, each (n, T) parameter pair yields a set of adjectives RTn, that is, the union of all sets {si}UCi,n with precision on the training set > T. A subset, ADJpses, of those sets is chosen based on precision and frequency in a validation set. Finally, the ADJpses are tested on the test set. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Table 7 shows the results for four opinion piece test sets. Multiple training-validation data set pairs are used for each test set, as given in Table 7. The results are for the union of the adjectives (verbs) chosen for each pair. The freq columns give total frequencies, and the +prec columns show the improvements in precision from the baseline. For each data set, the difference between the proportion of instances of ADJpses in opinion pieces and the proportion in nonopinion pieces is significant (p &lt; 0.001, z &gt; 9.2). The same is true for VERBpses (p &lt; 0.001, z &gt; 4.1). In the interests of testing consistency, Table 8 shows the results of assessing the adjective and verb features generated from opinion piece data (ADJpses and VERBpses Average frequencies and increases in precision in subjective-element data of the sets tested in Table 7. The baselines are the precisions of adjectives/verbs that appear in subjective elements in the subjective-element data. Frequencies and increases in precision for all features. For each data set, baseline frequency is the total number of words, and baseline precision is the proportion of words in opinion pieces. freq: total frequency; +prec: increase in precision over baseline. in Table 7) on the subjective-element data. The left side of the table gives baseline figures for each set of subjective-element annotations. The right side of the table gives the average frequencies and increases in precision over baseline for the ADJpses and VERBpses sets on the subjective-element data. The baseline figures in the table are the frequencies and precisions of the sets of adjectives and verbs that appear at least once in a subjective element. Since these sets include words that appear just once in the corpus (and thus have 100% precision), the baseline precision is a challenging one. 
                </paragraph> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Testing the VERBpses and ADJpses on the subjective-element data reveals some interesting consistencies for these subjectivity clues. The precision increases of the VERBpses on the subjective-element data are comparable to their increases on the opinion piece data. Similarly, the precision increases of the ADJpses on the subjective-element data are as good as or better than the performance of this set of PSEs on the opinion piece data. Finally, the precisions increases for the ADJpses are higher than for the VERBpses on all data sets. This is again consistent with the higher performance of the ADJpsessets in the opinion piece data sets. 
                </paragraph> 
            </subsection> 
        </section>
        <section imrad="r">
            <title>4. Features Used in Concert</title> 
            <subsection> 
                
                <title>4.1 Introduction</title> 
                <paragraph>
                    In this section, we examine the various types of clues used together. In preparation for this work, all instances in OP1 and OP2 of all of the PSEs identified as described in Section 3 have been automatically identified. All training to define the PSE instances in OP1 was performed on data separate from OP1, and all training to define the PSE instances in OP2 was performed on data separate from OP2. 
               
                </paragraph> 
                <title>4.2 Consistency in Precision among Data Sets</title> 
                <paragraph> 
                    Table 9 summarizes the results from previous sections in which the opinion piece data are used for testing. The performance of the various features is consistently good or bad on the same data sets: the performance is better for all features on W9-10 and W9-04 than on W9-22 and W9-33 (except for the ugen-4-grams, which occur with very low frequency, and the verbs, which have low frequency in W9-10). This is so despite the fact that the features were generated using different procedures and data: The 0. PSEs = all adjs, verbs, modals, nouns, and adverbs that appear at least once in an SE (except not, will, be, have). 1. PSEinsts = the set of all instances of PSEs 3. For P in PSEinsts: 4. leftWin(P) = the W words before P 5. rightWin(P) = the W words after P 6. density(P) = number of SEs whose first or last word is in leftWin(P) or rightWin(P) HiDensity = HiDensity u{P} number of PSEinsts in subject elements number of HiDensity in subject elements Figure 3 Algorithm for calculating density in subjective-element data. adjectives and verbs were generated from WSJ document-level opinion piece classifications; the n-gram features were generated from newsgroup and WSJ expression-level subjective-element classifications; and the unique unigram feature requires no training. This consistency in performance suggests that the results are not brittle. 
                </paragraph>
            </subsection>
            <title>4.3 Choosing Density Parameters from Subjective-Element Data</title> 
            <paragraph>
                   
                <context>
                    In <cite id="40" function="ack" polarity="neu">Wiebe (1994)</cite>, whether a PSE is interpreted to be subjective depends, in part, on how subjective the surrounding context is.
                </context>
                We explore this idea in the current work, assessing whether PSEs are more likely to be subjective if they are surrounded by subjective elements. In particular, we experiment with a density feature to decide whether or not a PSE instance is subjective: If a sufficient number of subjective elements are nearby, then the PSE instance is considered to be subjective; otherwise, it is discarded. The density parameters are a window size W and a frequency threshold T. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                In this section, we explore the density of manually annotated PSEs in subjective-element data and choose density parameters to use in Section 4.4, in which we apply them to automatically identified PSEs in opinion piece data. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The process for calculating density in the subjective-element data is given in Figure 3. The PSEs are defined to be all adjectives, verbs, modals, nouns, and adverbs that appear at least once in a subjective element, with the exception of some stop words (line 0 of Figure 3). Note that these PSEs depend only on the subjective-element manual annotations, not on the automatically identified features used elsewhere in the article or on the document-level opinion piece classes. PSEinsts is the set of PSE instances to be disambiguated (line 1). HiDensity (initialized on line 2) will be the subset of PSEinsts that are retained. In the loop, the density of each PSE instance P is calculated. This is the number of subjective elements that begin or end in the W words preceding or following P (line 6). P is retained if its density is at least T (line 7). 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Lines 8-9 of the algorithm assess the precision of the original (PSEinsts) and new (HiDensity) sets of PSE instances. If prec(HiDensity) is greater than prec(PSEinsts), then Most frequent entry in the top three precision intervals for each subjective-element data set. there is evidence that the number of subjective elements near a PSE instance is related to its subjectivity in context. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                To create more data points for this analysis, WSJ-SE was split into two (WSJ-SE1 and WSJ-SE2) and annotations of the two judges are considered separately. WSJ-SE2-D, for example, refers to D's annotations of WSJ-SE2. The process in Figure 3 was repeated for different parameter settings (T in [1,2,4,... ,48] and W in [1,10,20,..., 490]) on each of the SE data sets. To find good parameter settings, the results for each data set were sorted into five-point precision intervals and then sorted by frequency within each interval. Information for the top three precision intervals for each data set are shown in Table 10, specifically, the parameter values (i.e., T and W) and the frequency and precision of the most frequent result in each interval. The intervals are in the rows labeled Range. For example, the top three precision intervals for WSJ-SE1-M, 0.87-0.92, 0.82-0.87, and 0.77-0.82 (no parameter values yield higher precision than 0.92). The top of Table 10 gives baseline frequencies and precisions, which are \PSEinsts\ and prec(PSEinsts), respectively, in line 8 of Figure 3. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The parameter values exhibit a range of frequencies and precisions, with the expected trade-off between precision and frequency. We choose the following parameters to test in Section 4.4: For each data set, for each precision interval whose lower bound is at least 10 percentage points higher than the baseline for that data set, the top two (T, W) pairs yielding the highest frequencies in that interval are chosen. Among the five data sets, a total of 45 parameter pairs were so selected. This exercise was completed once, without experimenting with different parameter settings. 
            </paragraph> 
            <title>4.4 Density for Disambiguation</title> 
            <paragraph>  
                In this section, density is exploited to find subjective instances of automatically identified PSEs. The process is shown in Figure 4. There are only two differences between the algorithms in Figures 3 and 4. First, in Figure 3, density is defined in terms of the number of subjective elements nearby. However, subjective-element annotations are not available in test data. Thus in Figure 4, density is defined in terms of the HiDensity = HiDensity u{P} 0. PSEinsts = the set of instances in the test data of all PSEs described in Section 3 2. For P in PSEinsts: 3. leftWin(P) = the W words before P 4. rightWin(P) = the W words after P 5. density(P) = number of PSEinsts whose first or last word is in leftWin(P) or rightWin(P) 7. prec(PSEinsts) = #of^MEFJl^OPs o fTT-r^ m \ #of HiDensity in OPs 8. prec(HiDensity) = -HiDensity- Figure 4 Algorithm for calculating density in opinion piece (OP) data number of other PSE instances nearby, where PSEinsts consists of all instances of the automatically identified PSEs described in Section 3, for which results are given in Table 9. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Second, in Figure 4, we assess precision with respect to the document-level classes (lines 7-8). The test data are OP1. An interesting question arose when we were defining the PSE instances: What should be done with words that are identified to be PSEs (or parts of PSEs) according to multiple criteria? For example, sunny, radiant, and exhilarating are all unique in corpus OP1, and are all members of the adjective PSE feature defined for testing on OP1. Collocations add additional complexity. For example, consider the sequence and splendidly, which appears in the test data. The sequence and splendidly matches the ugen-2-gram (and-conj U-adj), and the word splendidly is unique. In addition, a sequence may match more than one n-gram feature. For example, is it that matches three fixed-n-gram features: is it, is it that, and it that. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                In the current experiments, the more PSEs a word matches, the more weight it is given. The hypothesis behind this treatment is that additional matches represent additional evidence that a PSE instance is subjective. This hypothesis is realized as follows: Each match of each member of each type of PSE is considered to be a PSE instance. Thus, among them, there are 11 members in PSEinsts for the five phrases sunny, radiant, exhilarating, and splendidly, and is it that, one for each of the matches mentioned above. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The process in Figure 4 was conducted with the 45 parameter pair values (T and W) chosen from the subjective-element data as described in Section 4.3. Table 11 shows results for a subset of the 45 parameters, namely, the most frequent parameter pair chosen from the top three precision intervals for each training set. The bottom of the table gives a baseline frequency and a baseline precision in OP1, defined as \PSEinsts\ and prec(PSEinsts), respectively, in line 7 of Figure 4. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The density features result in substantial increases in precision. Of the 45 parameter pairs, the minimum percentage increase over baseline is 22%. Fully 24% of the 45 parameter pairs yield increases of 200% or more; 38% yield increases between 100% Results for high-density PSEs in test data OP1 using parameters chosen from subjective-element data. and 199%, and 38% yield increases between 22% and 99%. In addition, the increases are significant. Using the set of high-density PSEs defined by the parameter pair with the least increase over baseline, we tested the difference in the proportion of PSEs in opinion pieces that are high-density and the proportion of PSEs in nonopinion pieces that are high-density. The difference between these two proportions is highly significant (z = 46.2, p &lt; 0.0001). 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Notice that, except for one blip (T, W = 6,10 under WSJ-SE-M), the precisions decrease and the frequencies increase as we go down each column in Table 11. The same pattern can be observed with all 45 parameter pairs (results not included here because of space considerations). But the parameter pairs are ordered in Table 11 based on performance in the manually annotated subjective-element data, not based on performance in the test data. For example, the entry in the first row, first column (T, W = 10,20) is the parameter pair giving the highest frequency in the top precision interval of WSJ-SE-M (frequency and precision in WSJ-SE-M, using the process of Figure 3). Thus, the relative precisions and frequencies of the parameter pairs are carried over from the training to the test data. This is quite a strong result, given that the PSEs in the training data are from manual annotations, while the PSEs in the test data are our automatically identified features. 
            </paragraph> 
            <title>4.5 High-Density Sentence Annotations</title> 
            <paragraph> 
                To assess the subjectivity of sentences with high-density PSEs, we extracted the 133 sentences in corpus OP2 that contain at least one high-density PSE and manually annotated them. We refer to these sentences as the system-identified sentences. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                We chose the density-parameter pair (T, W = 12,30), based on its precision and frequency in OP1. This parameter setting yields results that have relatively high precision and low frequency. We chose a low-frequency setting to make the annotation study feasible. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The extracted sentences were independently annotated by two judges. One is a coauthor of this article (judge 1), and the other has performed subjectivity annotation before, but is not otherwise involved in this research (judge 2).                <context>
                   <task> Sentences were annotated</task> <kw>according to</kw> the coding instructions of <cite id="41" function="bas" polarity="pos">Wiebe, Bruce, and O' Hara (1999)</cite> which, recall, are to classify a sentence as subjective if there is a significant expression of subjectivity of either the writer or someone mentioned in the text, in the sentence.
                </context>
                Sentence annotation contingency table; judge 1 counts are in rows and judge 2 counts are in columns. In addition to the subjective and objective classes, a judge can tag a sentence as unsure if he or she is unsure of his or her rating or considers the sentence to be borderline. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                An equal number (133) of other sentences were randomly selected from the corpus to serve as controls. The 133 system-identified sentences and the 133 control sentences were randomly mixed together. The judges were asked to annotate all 266 sentences, not knowing which were system-identified and which were control. Each sentence was presented with the sentence that precedes it and the sentence that follows it in the corpus, to provide some context for interpretation. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Table 12 shows examples of the system-identified sentences. Sentences classified by both judges as objective are marked oo and those classified by both judges as subjective are marked ss. Examples of subjective sentences adjacent to system-identified sentences. Bathed in cold sweat, I watched these Dantesque scenes, holding tightly the damp hand of Edek or Waldeck who, like me, were convinced that there was no God. "The Japanese are amazed that a company like this exists in Japan," says Kimindo Kusaka, head of the Softnomics Center, a Japanese management-research organization. And even if drugs were legal, what evidence do you have that the habitual drug user wouldn't continue to rob and steal to get money for clothes, food or shelter? The moral cost of legalizing drugs is great, but it is a cost that apparently lies outside the narrow scope of libertarian policy prescriptions. I doubt that one exists. They were upset at his committee's attempt to pacify the program critics by cutting the surtax paid by the more affluent elderly and making up the loss by shifting more of the burden to the elderly poor and by delaying some benefits by a year. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Judge 1 classified 103 of the system-identified sentences as subjective, 16 as objective, and 14 as unsure. Judge 2 classified 102 of the system-identified sentences as subjective, 27 as objective; and 4 as unsure. The contingency table is given in Table 13. The kappa value using all three classes is 0.60, reflecting the highly skewed distribution in favor of subjective sentences, and the disagreement on the lower-frequency classes (unsure and objective).
<context>
                <posfeature>Consistent with</posfeature> <result>the findings</result> <kw>in</kw> <cite id="42" function="ack" polarity="pos">Wiebe, Bruce, and O' Hara (1999)</cite>, the kappa value for agreement on the sentences for which neither judge is unsure is very high: 0.86. 
</context>
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                A different breakdown of the sentences is illuminating. For 98 of the sentences (call them SS), judges 1 and 2 tag the sentence as subjective. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Among the other sentences, 20 appear in a block of contiguous system-identified sentences that includes a member of SS. For example, in Table 12, (2.a) and (2.c) are in SS and (2.b) is in the same block of subjective sentences as they are. Similarly, (3.a) is in SS and (3.b) is in the same block. Among the remaining 15 sentences, 6 are adjacent to subjective sentences that were not identified by our system (so were not annotated by the judges). All of those sentences contain significant expressions of subjectivity of the writer or someone mentioned in the text, the criterion used in this work for classifying a sentence as subjective. Samples are shown in Table 14. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Thus, 93% of the sentences identified by the system are subjective or are near subjective sentences. All the sentences, together with their tags and the sentences adjacent to them, are available on the Web at www.cs.pitt.edu/~wiebe. 
            </paragraph> 
            <title>4.6 Using Features for Opinion Piece Recognition</title> 
            <paragraph> 
                In this section, we assess the usefulness of the PSEs identified in Section 3 and listed in Table 9 by using them to perform document-level classification of opinion pieces. Opinion-piece classification is a difficult task for two reasons. First, as discussed in Section 2.1, both opinionated and factual documents tend to be composed of a mixture of subjective and objective language. Second, the natural distribution of documents in our data is heavily skewed toward nonopinion pieces. Despite these hurdles, using only 4 In contrast, Judge 1 classified only 53 (45%) of the control sentences as subjective, and Judge 2 classified only 47 (36%) of them as subjective. our PSEs,
                <context>
                    <author>we</author> 
                    <kw>achieve positive results</kw> in opinion-piece classification <kw>using the</kw> basic <method>k-nearest-neighbor (KNN) algorithm</method> with leave-one-out cross-validation <cite id="43" function="bas" polarity="pos">(Mitchell 1997)</cite>.    
                </context>
                
                
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Given a document, the basic KNN algorithm classifies the document according to the majority classification of the document's k closest neighbors. For our purposes, each document is characterized by one feature, the count of all PSE instances (regardless of type) in the document, normalized by document length in words. The distance between two documents is simply the absolute value of the difference between the normalized PSE counts for the two documents. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                With leave-one-out cross-validation, the set of n documents to be classified is divided into a training set of size n — 1 and a validation set of size 1. The one document in the validation set is then classified according to the majority classification of its k closest-neighbor documents in the training set. This process is repeated until every document is classified. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Which value to use for k is chosen during a preprocessing phase. During the preprocessing phase, we run the KNN algorithm with leave-one-out cross-validation on a separate training set, for odd values of k from 1 to 15. The value of k that results in the best classification during the preprocessing phase is the one used for later KNN classification. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                For the classification experiment, the data set OP1 was used in the preprocessing phase to select the value of k, and then classification was performed on the 1,222 documents in OP2. During training on OP1, k equal to 15 resulted in the best classification. On the test set, OP2, we achieved a classification accuracy of 0.939; the baseline accuracy for choosing the most frequent class (nonopinion pieces) was 0.915. Our classification accuracy represents a 28% reduction in error and is significantly better than baseline according to McNemar's test (Everitt 1997). 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                The positive results from the opinion piece classification show the usefulness of the various PSE features when used together. 
            </paragraph> 
           
        </section> 
        <section imrad="d"> 
            <title>5. Relation to Other Work</title> 
            <paragraph> 
                There has been much work in other fields, including linguistics, literary theory, psychology, philosophy, and content analysis, involving subjective language. 
                <context>
                    As mentioned in Section 2, <concept>the conceptualization</concept> 
                    <kw>underlying</kw> 
                    <author>our</author> 
                    <data>manual annotations</data> 
                    <kw>is based on work</kw> in literary theory and linguistics, <kw>most directly</kw> 
                    <cite id="44" function="bas" polarity="pos">Dolezel (1973)</cite>, <cite id="45" function="bas" polarity="pos">Uspensky (1973)</cite>, <cite id="46" function="bas" polarity="pos">Kuroda (1973, 1976)</cite>, <cite id="47" function="bas" polarity="pos">Chatman (1978)</cite>, <cite id="48" function="bas" polarity="pos">Cohn (1978)</cite>, <cite id="49" function="bas" polarity="pos">Fodor (1979)</cite>, and <cite id="50" function="bas" polarity="pos">Banfield (1982)</cite>. 
                </context>
                <context>
                    <author>We</author> 
                    <kw>also mentioned</kw> 
                    <data>existing knowledge resources</data> 
                    <kw>such as</kw> affective lexicons <cite id="51" function="bas" polarity="pos">(General-Inquirer 2000; Heise 2000)</cite> and annotations in more general-purpose lexicons (e.g., the attitude adverb features in Comlex [Macleod, Grishman, and Meyers 1998]). 
                </context>
                Such knowledge may be used in future work to complement the work presented in this article, for example, to seed the distributional-similarity process described in Section 3.4. There is also work in fields such as content analysis and psychology on statistically characterizing texts in terms of word lists manually developed for distinctions related to subjectivity. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                <context>
                    For example, <cite id="52" function="use" polarity="neu">Hart (1984)</cite> 
                    <action>performs</action> 
                    <task>counts</task> 
                    <kw>on</kw> 
                    <data>a manually developed </data>list of words and rhetorical devices (e.g., "sacred" terms such as freedom) in political speeches to explore potential reasons for public reactions. 
                </context>
                <context>
                    <cite id="53" function="use" polarity="neu">  Anderson and McMaster (1998)</cite> 
                    <kw>use</kw> 
                    <data>fixed sets of high-frequency words</data> 
                    <kw>to</kw> 
                    <task>assign connotative scores to documents</task> and sections of documents along dimensions such as how pleasant, acrimonious, pious, or confident, the text is. 
                </context>
                What distinguishes our work from work on subjectivity in other fields is that we focus on (1) automatically learning knowledge from corpora, (2) automatically performing contextual disambiguation, and (3) using knowledge of subjectivity in NLP applications. 
                <context>
                    <author>This article</author> 
                    <kw>expands and integrates</kw> 
                    <kw>the work reported in</kw>  
                    <cite id="54" function="bas" polarity="pos">Wiebe and Wilson (2002)</cite>,  <cite id="55" function="bas" polarity="pos">Wiebe, Wilson, and Bell (2001)</cite>, <cite id="56" function="bas" polarity="pos">Wiebe et al. (2001)</cite> and <cite id="57" function="bas" polarity="pos">Wiebe (2000)</cite>. 
                </context>
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Previous work in NLP on the same or related tasks includes sentence-level and document-level subjectivity classifications. 
                
                <context>
                    At the sentence level, <cite id="58" function="use" polarity="neu">Wiebe, Bruce, and O' Hara (1999)</cite> 
                    <kw>developed</kw> 
                    <tool>a machine learning system</tool> 
                    <kw>to</kw> 
                    <task>classify sentences as subjective or objective</task>
                </context>
                
                
                The accuracy of the system was more than 20 percentage points higher than a baseline accuracy. Five part-of-speech features, two lexical features, and a paragraph feature were used. These results suggested to us that there are clues to subjectivity that might be learned automatically from text and motivated the work reported in the current article. The system was tested in 10-fold cross validation experiments using corpus WSJ-SE, a small corpus of only 1,001 sentences. As discussed in Section 1, a main goal of our current work is to exploit existing document-level annotations, because they enable us to use much larger data sets, they were created outside our research group, and they allow us to assess consistency of performance by cross-validating between our manual annotations and the existing document-level annotations. Because the document-level data are not annotated at the sentence level, sentence-level classification is not highlighted in this article. The new sentence annotation study to evaluate sentences with high-density features (Section 4.5) uses different data from WSJ-SE, because some of the features (n-grams and density parameters) were identified using WSJ-SE as training data. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Other previous work in NLP has addressed related document-level classifications. <cite id="30">Spertus (1997)</cite> developed a system for recognizing inflammatory messages. As mentioned earlier in the article, inflammatory language is a type of subjective language, so the task she addresses is closely related to ours. She uses machine learning to select among manually developed features. In contrast, the focus in our work is on automatically identifying features from the data. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                A number of projects investigating genre detection include editorials as one of the targeted genres. 
                <context>
                    For example, in  <cite id="59" function="ack" polarity="neu">Karlgren and Cutting (1994)</cite>, editorials are one of fifteen categories, and in  <cite id="60" function="ack" polarity="neu">Kessler, Nunberg, and Schutze (1997)</cite>, editorials are one of six. 
                </context>
                Given the goal of these works to perform genre detection in general, they use low-level features that are not specific to editorials. Neither shows significant improvements for editorial recognition.  
                <context>
                    <cite id="61" function="ack" polarity="neu">Argamon, Koppel, and Avneri (1998)</cite> address a slightly different task, though it does involve editorials. Their goal is to distinguish not only, for example, news from editorials, but also these categories in different publications.
                </context>
                Their best results are distinguishing among the news categories of different publications; their lowest results involve editorials. Because we focus specifically on distinguishing opinion pieces from nonopinion pieces, our results are better than theirs for those categories. In addition, in contrast to the above studies, the focus of our work is on learning features of subjectivity. We perform opinion piece recognition in order to assess the usefulness of the various features when used together. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                <context>
                    Other <kw>previous</kw> NLP research 
                    has used
                    features
                    <kw>similar to ours</kw> for other NLP tasks. Low-frequency words have been used as features in information extraction <cite id="62" function="con" polarity="neu">(Weeber, Vos, and Baayen 2000)</cite> and text categorization <cite id="63" function="con" polarity="neu">(Copeck et al. 2000)</cite></context>. <context>A number of researchers have worked on mining collocations from text to extend lexicographic resources for machine translation and word sense disambiguation <cite id="64" function="ack" polarity="neu">(e.g., Smajda 1993; Lin 1999; Biber 1993)</cite>. 
                </context>
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                <context>
                    In <cite id="65" function="con" polarity="neu">Samuel, Carberry, and Vijay-Shanker's (1998)</cite> 
                   work on 
                    identifying collocations for dialog-act recognition, a filter
                    <kw>similar to ours</kw> was used to eliminate redundant n-gram features: n-grams were eliminated if they contained substrings with the same entropy score as or a better entropy score than the n-gram. 
                </context>
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph>  
                <context>
                    While <kw>it is common in</kw> 
                    <experiment>studies of collocations</experiment> 
                    <negfeature>to omit low-frequency words and expressions</negfeature> from analysis, because they give rise to invalid or unrealistic statistical measures (<cite id="66" function="wea" polarity="neg">Church and Hanks, 1990</cite>), <author>we</author> 
                    <posfeature>are able to identify higher-precision collocations</posfeature> by including placeholders for unique words (i.e., the ugen-n-grams).
                </context>
                We are not aware of other work that uses such collocations as we do. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                <context>
                    <feature>Features</feature> 
                    <kw>identified using</kw> 
                    <method>distributional similarity</method> 
                    <kw>have previously been used</kw> for syntactic and semantic disambiguation <cite id="67" function="bas" polarity="pos">(Hindle 1990; Dagan, Pereira, and Lee 1994)</cite> and to develop lexical resources from corpora <cite id="68" function="bas" polarity="pos">(Lin 1998; Riloff and Jones 1999)</cite>. 
                </context>
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                We are not aware of other work identifying and using density parameters as described in this article. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Since our experiments, other related work in NLP has been performed. Some of this work addresses related but different classification tasks. Three studies classify reviews as positive or negative (Turney 2002; Pang, Lee, and Vaithyanathan 2002; Dave, Lawrence, Pennock 2003). The input is assumed to be a review, so this task does not include finding subjective documents in the first place. 
                <context>
                    <experiment>The first study </experiment>listed above <cite id="69" function="ack" polarity="neu">(Turney 2002)</cite> 
                    <kw>uses a variation of</kw> 
                    <method>the semantic similarity procedure</method> presented in <cite id="70" function="ack" polarity="neu">Wiebe (2000)</cite> 
                </context>
                <context>
                    (Section 3.4). The third <cite id="71" function="ack" polarity="neu">(Dave, Lawrence, and Pennock 2003)</cite> uses n-gram features identified with a variation of the procedure presented in  <cite id="72" function="ack" polarity="neu">Wiebe, Wilson, and Bell (2001)</cite> (Section 3.3).
                </context>
                <context>
                    <cite id="73" function="wea" polarity="neg">Tong (2001)</cite> 
                    <kw>addresses</kw> 
                    <task>finding sentiment timelines</task>, that is, tracking sentiments over time in multiple documents. For clues of subjectivity, <kw>he uses</kw> 
                    <negfeature>manually developed lexical rules</negfeature>, <kw>rather than</kw> 
                    <posfeature>automatically learning</posfeature> them from corpora. <kw>Similarly</kw>, <cite id="74" function="wea" polarity="neg">Gordon et al. (2003)</cite> use <negfeature>manually developed grammars</negfeature> to detect some types of subjective language.
                </context>
                <context>
                    <cite id="75" function="wea" polarity="neg">Agrawal et al. (2003)</cite> 
                    <task>partition newsgroup authors into camps</task> based on quotation links. <negfeature>They do not attempt to recognize subjective language</negfeature>. 
                </context>
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                <context>
                    <kw>The most closely</kw> 
                    <kw>related</kw> 
                    <experiment>new work</experiment> is  <cite id="76" function="use" polarity="pos">Riloff, Wiebe, and Wilson (2003)</cite>, <cite id="77" function="use" polarity="pos">Riloff and  Wiebe (2003)</cite> and  <cite id="78" function="use" polarity="pos">Yu and Hatzivassiloglou (2003)</cite>. The first two focus on finding additional types of subjective clues (nouns and extraction patterns identified using extraction pattern bootstrapping).
                </context>
                <context>
                    <cite id="79" function="use" polarity="pos"> Yu and Hatzivassiloglou (2003)</cite> 
                    <kw>perform</kw> 
                    <task>opinion text classification</task>.
                </context>

                They also use existing WSJ document classes for training and testing, but they do not include the entire corpus in their experiments, as we do. Their opinion piece class consists only of editorials and letters to the editor, and their nonopinion class consists only of business and news. They report an average F-measure of 96.5%. Our result of 94% accuracy on document level classification is almost comparable. They also perform sentence-level classification. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                We anticipate that knowledge of subjective language may be usefully exploited in a number of NLP application areas and hope that the work presented in this article will encourage others to experiment with subjective language in their applications.
                <context>
                    More generally, <kw>there are many types of</kw> 
                    <tool>artificial intelligence systems</tool> for which state-of-affairs types such as beliefs and desires are central, including systems <kw>that perform</kw> 
                    <task>plan recognition for understanding narratives</task> 
                    <cite id="80" function="use" polarity="neu">(Dyer 1982; Lehnert et al. 1983)</cite>, <task>for argument understanding </task>
                    <cite id="81" function="use" polarity="neu">(Alvarado, Dyer, and Flowers 1986)</cite>, <task>for understanding stories</task> from different perspectives <cite id="82" function="use" polarity="neu">(Carbonell 1979)</cite>, and for <task>generating language</task> under different pragmatic constraints <cite id="83" function="use" polarity="neu">(Hovy 1987)</cite>. 
                </context>
                Knowledge of linguistic subjectivity could enhance the abilities of such systems to recognize and generate expressions referring to such states of affairs in natural text. 
            </paragraph> 
      
        
            <title>6. Conclusions</title> 
            <paragraph> 
                Knowledge of subjective language promises to be beneficial for many NLP applications including information extraction, question answering, text categorization, and summarization. This article has presented the results of an empirical study in acquiring knowledge of subjective language from corpora in which a number of feature types were learned and evaluated on different types of data with positive results. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                We showed that unique words are subjective more often than expected and that unique words are valuable clues to subjectivity. We also presented a procedure for automatically identifying potentially subjective collocations, including fixed collocations and collocations with placeholders for unique words. In addition, we used the results of a method for clustering words according to distributional similarity (Lin 1998) to identify adjectival and verbal clues of subjectivity. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Table 9 summarizes the results of testing all of the above types of PSEs. All show increased precision in the evaluations. Together, they show consistency in performance. In almost all cases they perform better or worse on the same data sets, despite the fact that different kinds of data and procedures are used to learn them. In addition, PSEs learned using expression-level subjective-element data have precisions higher than baseline on document-level opinion piece data, and vice versa. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Having a large stable of PSEs, it was important to disambiguate whether or not PSE instances are subjective in the contexts in which they appear. We discovered that the density of other potentially subjective expressions in the surrounding context is important. If a clue is surrounded by a sufficient number of other clues, then it is more likely to be subjective than if there were not. Parameter values were selected using training data manually annotated at the expression level for subjective elements and then tested on data annotated at the document level for opinion pieces. All of the selected parameters led to increases in precision on the test data, and most lead to increases over 100%. Once again we found consistency between expression-level and document-level annotations. PSE sets defined by density have high precision in both the subjective-element data and the opinion piece data. The large differences between training and testing suggest that our results are not brittle. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Using a density feature selected from a training set, sentences containing high-density PSEs were extracted from a separate test set, and manually annotated by two judges. Fully 93% of the sentences extracted were found to be subjective or to be near subjective sentences. Admittedly, the chosen density feature is a high-precision, low-frequency one. But since the process is fully automatic, the feature could be applied to more unannotated text to identify regions containing subjective sentences. In addition, because the precision and frequency of the density features are stable across data sets, lower-precision but higher-frequency options are available. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Finally, the value of the various types of PSEs was demonstrated with the task of opinion piece classification. Using the k-nearest-neighbor classification algorithm with leave-one-out cross-validation, a classification accuracy of 94% was achieved on a large test set, with a reduction in error of 28% from the baseline. 
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                Future work is required to determine how to exploit density features to improve the performance of text categorization algorithms.
                <context>
                    Another area of future work is searching for clues to objectivity, such as the politeness features used by <cite id="84" function="ack" polarity="neu">Spertus (1997)</cite>. 
                </context>
                <context>
                
                    Still another is identifying the type of a subjective expression (e.g., positive or negative evaluative), extending work such as  <cite id="85" function="ack" polarity="neu">Hatzivassiloglou and McKeown (1997)</cite> on classifying lexemes to the classification of instances in context (compare, e.g., "great!" and "oh great.") 
                </context>
            </paragraph> 
            <paragraph> 
                In addition, it would be illuminating to apply our system to data annotated with discourse trees (Carlson, Marcu, and Okurowski 2001). We hypothesize that most objective sentences identified by our system are dominated in the discourse by subjective sentences and that we are moving toward identifying subjective discourse segments. 
            </paragraph> 
       
            <title>Acknowledgments</title> 
            <paragraph> 
                We thank the anonymous reviewers for their helpful and constructive comments. This research was supported in part by the Office of Naval Research under grants N00014-95-1-0776 and N00014-01-1-0381. 
            </paragraph> 
        </section> 
    </paper>
</annotatedpaper>